So let's talk about the other way
Hãy nói về cách khác
to run containers onto AWS, and this is using Amazon EKS.
để chạy container trên AWS, đó là dùng Amazon EKS.
So Amazon EKS stands for Amazon Elastic Kubernetes Service.
Amazon EKS viết tắt của Amazon Elastic Kubernetes Service.
So it is a way, as the name indicates,
Đây là cách, như tên gọi,
to launch and manage Kubernetes cluster onto AWS.
để khởi chạy và quản lý cụm Kubernetes trên AWS.
So what is Kubernetes?
Kubernetes là gì?
Well, this is the blue logo
Đó là logo màu xanh
you see in the top right corner of the screen.
bạn thấy ở góc phải trên màn hình.
Kubernetes is an open-source system
Kubernetes là hệ thống mã nguồn mở
for automatic deployments, scaling and management
để tự động triển khai, mở rộng và quản lý
of containerized, usually Docker, applications.
các ứng dụng container hóa, thường là Docker.
So it is an alternative to ECS, which has a similar goal
Nó là lựa chọn thay thế cho ECS với mục tiêu tương tự
which is to run your containers, but a very different API.
là chạy container nhưng API rất khác.
The idea is that ECS is definitely not open-source.
ECS rõ ràng không phải mã nguồn mở.
Whereas Kubernetes is open-source
Trong khi Kubernetes mã nguồn mở
and used by many different cloud providers
và được nhiều nhà cung cấp đám mây dùng
which gives you some sort of standardization.
mang lại sự chuẩn hóa.
So EKS supports two launch modes,
EKS hỗ trợ hai chế độ triển khai,
again the EC2 launch mode if you want to deploy
chế độ EC2 nếu bạn muốn triển khai
worker mode like EC2 instances,
các worker là EC2,
or the Fargate mode if you wanted to deploy
hoặc chế độ Fargate nếu muốn triển khai
serverless containers in an EKS cluster.
container serverless trong cụm EKS.
So the use case for using EKS is that your company
Trường hợp dùng EKS là khi công ty bạn
is already using Kubernetes on-premises,
đã dùng Kubernetes on-premises,
or already using Kubernetes in another cloud,
hoặc trên đám mây khác,
or they just want use the Kubernetes API,
hoặc chỉ muốn dùng API Kubernetes,
and they want to use AWS to manage the Kubernetes cluster,
và muốn AWS quản lý cụm Kubernetes,
then they would use Amazon EKS.
thì sẽ dùng Amazon EKS.
So again, Kubernetes from an exam perspective,
Trong kỳ thi, Kubernetes
is cloud agnostic, it can be used into any cloud
độc lập nền tảng, có thể dùng trên bất kỳ cloud nào
such as Azure, Google Cloud and so on.
như Azure, Google Cloud, v.v.
And so that means that if you are trying to migrate
Vì vậy nếu bạn muốn di chuyển
between clouds or your containers,
giữa các đám mây hoặc container,
using Amazon EKS may be a much more simple solution.
sử dụng Amazon EKS có thể đơn giản hơn nhiều.
So in terms of diagram, this is what it looks like.
Về sơ đồ, nó trông như thế này.
So we have a VPC, 3 AZ separated
Chúng ta có VPC, 3 AZ tách biệt
into public subnets and private subnets.
thành subnet công khai và riêng tư.
And so you would create EKS Worker Nodes
Bạn sẽ tạo các EKS Worker Node
they would be EC2 instances for example,
ví dụ là EC2 instance,
and each of these nodes will be running EKS Pods.
và mỗi node chạy các EKS Pod.
So they're very similar to ECS tasks,
Chúng rất giống ECS task,
but from a naming perspective,
nhưng về thuật ngữ,
anytime you see pods, it relates to Amazon Kubernetes, okay?
thấy 'pod' là liên quan Kubernetes.
So we have EKS Pods and they're running onto EKS Nodes,
Chúng ta có EKS Pod chạy trên EKS Node,
and so these nodes can be managed by an Auto Scaling group.
các node có thể được quản lý bởi Auto Scaling Group.
Now, very similarly to ECS,
Tương tự ECS,
if you wanted to expose EKS Service and Kubernetes Service,
nếu bạn muốn expose EKS/Kubernetes Service,
we could set up a private load balancer,
ta có thể thiết lập load balancer nội bộ,
or a public load balancer to talk to the web.
hoặc load balancer công khai để ra web.
So let's summarize the different node types
Hãy tổng kết các loại node
that exist for Amazon EKS.
trong Amazon EKS.
So you have the Manage Node Groups,
Bạn có Manage Node Group,
and this is AWS that will create and manage Nodes,
AWS sẽ tạo và quản lý các node,
so EC2 instances for you.
tức các EC2 instance.
And these nodes are part of an Auto Scaling group,
Các node này thuộc một Auto Scaling Group,
managed by the EKS service itself.
được dịch vụ EKS quản lý.
And you have support for On-Demand and Spot Instances.
Hỗ trợ On-Demand và Spot Instance.
You can also choose if you wanted to,
Bạn cũng có thể chọn
to self-manage nodes, this is if you want to have
tự quản lý node nếu muốn
more customizations and more control.
tùy chỉnh và kiểm soát nhiều hơn.
So in that case you need to create the nodes yourself,
Khi đó bạn phải tự tạo node,
and then you need to register them to an EKS cluster,
đăng ký chúng vào cụm EKS,
and then you manage your own nodes as part of an ASG.
và quản lý chúng như một ASG.
You can still use the pre-built Amazon EKS Optimized AMI
Bạn vẫn có thể dùng AMI tối ưu sẵn của EKS
for this, which saves you a bit of time,
để tiết kiệm thời gian,
or you can build your own AMI, which is more complicated.
hoặc tự tạo AMI của bạn, phức tạp hơn.
This supports as well, the On-Demand and the Spot Instances.
Cách này cũng hỗ trợ On-Demand và Spot.
And finally, if you don't wanna see any nodes at all,
Cuối cùng, nếu bạn không muốn thấy node nào,
then Amazon EKS, as I told you, supports the Fargate mode
Amazon EKS hỗ trợ chế độ Fargate
in which there is no maintenance required,
không cần bảo trì,
and no nodes are managed at all you can just run containers
không quản lý node, chỉ chạy container
on top of Amazon EKS.
trên Amazon EKS.
Now you can attach data volumes to your Amazon EKS cluster.
Bạn có thể gắn volume dữ liệu vào cụm EKS.
For this, you need to specify a StorageClass manifest
Bạn cần khai báo manifest StorageClass
on your EKS cluster, and this leverages something called
trên cụm EKS, sử dụng
the Container Storage Interface, CSI compliant driver.
trình điều khiển CSI (Container Storage Interface).
So keywords to look out for at the exam.
Những từ khóa cần nhớ cho kỳ thi.
And you have support for Amazon EBS,
Có hỗ trợ Amazon EBS,
you have support for Amazon EFS, and this is the only type
hỗ trợ Amazon EFS, và đây là loại duy nhất
of storage class that works with Fargate.
kiểu lưu trữ hoạt động với Fargate.
You have Amazon FSx for Lustre
Có Amazon FSx for Lustre
and Amazon FSx for NetApp ONTAP.
và Amazon FSx for NetApp ONTAP.
So that's it for Amazon EKS.
Đó là tất cả về Amazon EKS.
I hope you liked it and I will see you in the next lecture.
Hy vọng bạn thích, hẹn gặp lại ở bài giảng tiếp theo.